A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, M-R FA393
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Miller, Harry M.
  - 1937 June 4-December 20, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 212 pages (Box 328, Reel M Mil 2, Frame 551)
    Wales; Zoology; Czechoslovakia; England; Embryology; Anatomy; Switzerland; Chemistry; Austria; Physiology; Plant pathology; Pharmacology; Physics; Diaries; Germany; Italy
  - 1938, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 227 pages (Box 328, Reel M Mil 2, Frame 774)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. In 1938, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers. The diary includes memorandum, travelogue, photographs and an agenda for "Discussion Meeting on The Protein Molecule."
    France; Finland; Endocrinology; Embryology; Estonia; England; Diaries; Sweden; Zoology; Lithuania; Latvia; Hungary; Germany; Sex; Physiology; Nutrition; Netherlands; Chemistry; Czechoslovakia; Denmark; Genetics; Biology -- Research; Botany; Canada
  - 1939 January 9-June 20, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 182 pages (Box 328, Reel M Mil 2, Frame 1,024)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. In 1939, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers. The diary includes memorandum and travelogue.
    Botany; Biology -- Research; Biochemistry; France; England; Diaries; Cytology; Plant pathology; Physics; Netherlands; Histology; Zoology; Scotland
  - 1939 June 20-December 16, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 178 pages (Box 329, Reel M Mil 3, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. In 1939, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers. Details of European build up to World War II are given. The diary includes memorandum, travelogue, letters, and status reports of RF projects and grants in Paris and England.
    Biochemistry; Zoology; Physics; France; World War II; Diaries; Physiology; Denmark; Biology -- Research; England
  - Index, 1940 April 17-1941 December 22; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M. (Reel M Mil 3, Frame 188, Box 329)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. In 1940, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers. Miller attends the Conference on Science, Philosophy and Religion, and Conference on Applied Nuclear Physics. The diary includes memorandum and travelogue.
    Histology; Europe; Netherlands; indexes (reference sources); Agriculture; Embryology; Biology -- Research; Physics; Portugal; Nuclear physics; Philosophy and religion
  - 1940, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 194 pages (Reel M Mil 3, Frame 212, Box 329)
    Diaries; Physics; Portugal; Netherlands; Philosophy and religion; Europe; Histology; Embryology; Agriculture; Biology -- Research
  - 1941 January 2-April 1, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 201 pages (Reel M Mil 3, Frame 412, Box 329)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. In 1941, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers to assess RF projects. Miller goes to Mexico to survey agriculture.
    Agriculture; Biology -- Research; Zoology; United States; Diaries; Physics; Mexico; Immunology; Genetics; Chemistry
  - 1941 April 7-December 22, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 24 pages
    United States; Diaries; Physics; Agriculture; Biology -- Research
  - Index, 1942 January 7- 1944 August 23; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M. (Box 329, Reel M Mil 3, Frame 719)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers to assess RF projects. He attends the "Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Exchange Fellowships under the Convention for the Promotion of Inter-American Cultural Relations", interviews Latin American research scientists, and coordinates the Mexican Agriculture Program. Miller also attends the Meeting to Consider Policy on NS Program in Latin America.
    United States; Peru; Mexico; indexes (reference sources); Genetics; Colombia; Biology -- Research; Agriculture; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George)
  - Table of Contents, 1942-1944; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.
  - 1942-1944, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences
    Agriculture; Diaries; United States; Biology -- Research; Physics
  - Index to Trip to Mexico, Central America and Columbia, 1942 March 20-April 20; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences
  - Trip to Mexico, Central America, and Colombia, 1942 March 20-April 10; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 56 pages (Box 329, Reel M Mil 3, Frame 859)
    Miller travels to Mexico, Central America and Columbia to survey for possible RF program investment.
    Biology -- Research; Agriculture; Colombia; Chemistry; Diaries; Costa Rica; Guatemala; Education; Mexico; Hygiene; Panama
  - Index, 1945; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 329, Reel M Mil 3, Frame 923)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Frank B. Hanson
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers to assess RF projects. Miller attends Conference to Discuss Plans for Administration of Predoctoral Fellowship in the Natural Sciences under RF Grant to NRC, and Mexican Agriculture Annual Meeting.
    Plant pathology; United States; Zoology; Agriculture; Botany; Biology -- Research; indexes (reference sources); Genetics; National Research Council. (U.S.); Harrar, J. George (Jacob George)
  - 1945, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry L.
    United States; Diaries; Biology -- Research
  - Index, 1946; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences
  - 1946, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 164 pages (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers to assess RF projects.
    Zoology; Diaries; Venezuela; Uruguay; United States; Peru; Nutrition; Genetics; Colombia; Chile; Brazil; Biology -- Research; Argentina; Agriculture
  - Index, 1947; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 188)
    21 pages.
    Honduras; Costa Rica; Colombia; Panama; Mexico; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1947, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 173 pages (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 209)
    Diaries; Sociology; Panama; Plant pathology; Agriculture; Costa Rica; Colombia; Botany; Agronomy; Mexico; Honduras; Genetics
  - Index, 1948; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M. (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 387)
    15 pages.
    Argentina; indexes (reference sources); Italy; Colombia; France; United States; Uruguay; Peru; Switzerland
  - 1948, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 164 pages (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 402)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers in Latin and South America for RF projects. The diary includes an interview with Dr. John E. Flynn, Editor-in-Chief, and "Biological Abstracts."
    Biology -- Research; Diaries; Colombia; Agronomy; Argentina; France; Italy; Fertility; Uruguay; Agriculture; Peru; Medicine; United States; Switzerland
  - Index, 1949; Pearce, Richard Mills; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Reel M Mil 4, Frame 571, Box 330)
    United States; Venezuela; indexes (reference sources); Mexico; Peru; Puerto Rico; Costa Rica; Colombia; Honduras; Dominican Republic; Chile; Brazil
  - 1949, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 201 pages (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 592)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers in Latin and South America for the RF agriculture program and other projects. Miller attends UN Scientific Conference on the Construction and Utilization of Resources.
    United States; Puerto Rico; Philosophy and religion; Peru; Nutrition; Agriculture; Agronomy; Botany; Venezuela; Mexico; Hygiene; Costa Rica; Colombia; Chile; Diaries; Brazil; Honduras; Dominican Republic; Domestic animals
  - Index, 1950; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M. (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 796)
    11 pages.
    Mexico; Panama; Jamaica; indexes (reference sources); Honduras; Haiti; El Salvador; Costa Rica; Colombia
  - 1950 January 4-May 31, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 106 pages (Reel M Mil 4, Frame 807, Box 330)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers in Latin and South America for the RF agriculture program and other projects. Miller attends Meeting of Directors of "Central American" Agricultural Experiment Agencies.
    Diaries; Jamaica; Honduras; Nutrition; Mexico; Zoology; Panama; Agriculture; Colombia; Agronomy; Costa Rica; Haiti; El Salvador
  - 1950 June 1-December 27, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 125 pages (Box 330, Reel M Mil 4, Frame 914)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and experiment stations in Latin and South America for the RF agriculture program.
    Diaries; Agronomy; Agriculture; Bolivia; Biology -- Research; Uruguay; Zoology; Peru; United States; Domestic animals; Plant pathology; Philosophy and religion; Brazil; Botany; Colombia
  - Index, 1951; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture (Reel M Mil 4, Frame 1,045, Box 331)
    10 pages.
    Brazil; Chile; Peru; indexes (reference sources); Ecuador; Colombia; Uruguay; United States
  - 1951, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; 158 pages (Reel M Mil 4, Frame 1,055, Box 331)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. The focus of Natural Science research is experimental biology. Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and experiment stations in Latin and South America for the RF agriculture program. Miller asks for recommendations for an agriculture program in Peru, assesses the Chilean Agricultural Program and details revolution in Argentina.
    Domestic animals; Ecuador; Peru; Botany; Brazil; Chile; Colombia; Philosophy and religion; Plant pathology; Biology -- Research; Agronomy; Agriculture; Diaries; United States; Uruguay
  - Index, 1952; Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture (Reel M Mil 5, Frame 1, Box 331)
    indexes (reference sources); Mexico; United States; Brazil; Chile; Colombia
  - 1952, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; 161 pages (Reel M Mil 5, Frame 12, Box 331)
    Diaries; Agriculture; Biology -- Research; Botany; Brazil; Chemistry; Colombia; Chile; Mexico; United States; Nutrition; Zoology
  - Index, 1953 (Box 331, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 188)
  - 1953 (Box 331, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 199)
  - Index, 1954 (Box 331, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 375)
  - 1954 (Reel M Mil 5, Frame 392, Box 331)
  - Index, 1955 (Box 331, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 554)
  - 1955 (Box 331, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 565)
  - Index, 1956 (Box 332, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 729)
  - 1956 (Box 332, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 740)
  - Index, 1957 (Box 332, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 913)
  - 1957 (Reel M Mil 5, Frame 924, Box 332)
  - 1958 (Box 332, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 1,049)
  - 1959 (Box 332, Reel M Mil 5, Frame 1,103)
- Miller, Leonard F.
  - 1970-1976 (Box 333)
- Molloy, Daniel M.
  - 1938 (Box 333)
- Morison, Robert Swain
  - 1944-1945 (Box 333)
  - 1946 January-June (Box 333)
  - 1946 July-December (Box 334)
  - 1947 (Box 334)
  - 1948 (Box 334)
  - 1949 (Box 335)
  - 1950 (Box 335)
  - 1951 (Box 335)
  - 1952 (Box 336)
  - 1953 (Box 336)
  - 1954 (Box 336)
  - 1955 (Box 337)
  - 1956 (Box 337)
  - 1957 (Box 337)
  - 1958 (Box 338)
  - 1959 (Box 338)
  - 1960 (Box 338)
  - 1961 (Box 338)
  - Diary, Index, 1962-1964 (Box 339)
- Moseman, Albert H.
  - 1956-1957 (Box 339)
  - 1958 (Box 340)
  - 1959 (Box 340)
  - 1960 (Box 341)
  - 1961 (Box 341)
  - 1962 (Box 342)
  - 1963 (Box 342)
  - 1964 (Box 343)
  - 1965 (Box 343)
- Muench, Hugo, Jr.
  - 1927 (Box 344)
  - 1932-1935 (Box 344)
  - 1937-1938 (Box 344)
  - 1939 (Box 344)
  - 1940 (Box 345)
  - 1941 (Box 345)
  - 1942 (Box 345)
  - 1943 (Box 345)
  - 1944-1946 (Box 346)
- Myers, Will M.
  Japan; Africa; India
  - 1965-1966 (Box 346)
  - 1967 (Box 347)
  - 1967 September-1968 December (Box 347)
  - Index (Box 347)
  - 1969 January-May (Box 347)
- Neumann, Ellsworth T.
  - 1973-1976 (Box 347)
    See also- Kenneth Wernimont, 1971-1974.
- Nickel, John L.
  - 1966-1967 October (Box 347)
  - 1967 November-1969 April (Box 347)
  - 1969 April-1970 January (Box 347)
  - 1970 February (Box 348)
  - 1971 (Box 348)
- Niederhauser, John S.
  John S. Niederhauser was a renowned plant pathologist who spent nearly three decades working for Rockefeller Foundation (RF) agricultural programs in Mexico. He earned international acclaim (and the nickname "Mr. Potato") for his extensive research, education, and collaboration on potato development programs and global food production challenges.
  Niederhauser was born in Seattle, Washington on September 27, 1916. In 1933 he received a scholarship to attend Deep Springs College in California, which featured a three-year program combining traditional academic study and farm labor. After completing his third year at Deep Springs, Niederhauser was eager to travel. He bought a steamship ticket to the Soviet Union and spent the summer working on a collective farm in the Ukrainian countryside. At the invitation of Russian plant geneticist Nikolai Vavilov, Niederhauser spent a year studying at the Timiryazev All-Union Academy for Agricultural Sciences in Moscow before returning to the United States in the fall of 1936. He finished his undergraduate work at Cornell University in 1939 and went on to earn his Ph.D. in plant pathology from Cornell in 1943.
  In 1946, Niederhauser joined the RF's Mexican Agricultural Program (MAP) which focused on improving Mexican agricultural yields. Working under the direction of plant pathologist George Harrar, Niederhauser initially studied diseases in wheat, maize, and beans. He soon narrowed his focus to Mexican potato production.
  In 1952, Harrar created a potato production program under Niederhauser's direction. The program sought to increase Mexican potato yields and investigate potato diseases, and was successful on both fronts. Niederhauser discovered that late blight, the potato disease responsible for the Irish potato famine in the 1840s, originated in Mexico. He also determined that resistance to late blight disease could be found in inedible wild potato species, which allowed him to breed new resistant potato varieties. His work dramatically increased potato yields in Mexico and around the world.
  Niederhauser worked diligently to educate fellow scientists about potato production and foster global collaborations to address food production challenges. He formed the Inter-American Potato Program, a unit within the Inter-American Food Crop Improvement Program created by the RF in 1961. In 1966, the name was changed to the International Potato Improvement Program to encompass the program's expanding global efforts. Niederhauser then went on to co-found the International Potato Center in Lima, Peru, in 1971, before resigning from the RF in 1973. In 1978 he helped establish the Regional Cooperative Potato Program (PRECODEPA) to foster regional collaboration between agricultural programs in Mexico, Central America, and the Caribbean.
  Niederhauser was awarded the World Food Prize in 1990 for his work to develop disease-resistant potato varieties and increase worldwide potato production.
  John Niederhauser died on August 12, 2005.
  - 1960 March (Box 348)
- Noll, Anna Mary
  - 1947-1948 (Box 348)
  - 1949-1951 (Box 348)
- Nolte, Richard H.
  - 1958 (Box 349)
  - 1959 (Box 349)
- Northrup, Robert S.
  - 1974-1977 (Box 349)
- Novak, Michael
  - 1973-1974 (Box 350)
- Nyberg, Albert J.
  - 1973-1977 (Box 350)
- O'Brien, Daniel P.
  - 1926-1928 (Box 350)
  - 1929 (Box 350)
  - 1930 (Box 351)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 351)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 351)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 351)
  - 1940, 1945, 1947 (Box 352)
- O'Connor, Francis William
  - 1924-1925 (Box 352)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 352)
- Ohlson, Virginia M.
  - 1952-1954 (Box 353)
- Oliver, Wade W.
  - 1948 January-June (Box 353)
  - 1948 July-December (Box 353)
  - 1949 (Box 354)
  - 1950 (Box 354)
  - 1951 (Box 354)
  - 1952 (Box 355)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 355)
  - 1955 (Box 355)
  - 1956 (Box 356)
- Olson, James A.
  - 1968 (Box 356)
- Olson, William C.
  - 1967 (Box 356)
  - 1968 (Box 356)
  - 1969 (Box 357)
- Ordway, Nelson K.
  - 1965 (Box 357)
- Osler, Robert D.
  - 1960-1961 (Box 357)
  - 1962 (Box 358)
  - 1963 (Box 358)
  - 1964 (Box 358)
  - 1965 (Box 359)
  - 1966 (Box 359)
- Owens, Patrick N.
  - 1962-1968 (Box 359)
  - 1969-1973 (Box 360)
- Padgett, L. Vincent
  - 1965-1966 (Box 360)
- Parker, Dorothy
  Dorothy Inez Parker was a botanist, librarian, bibliographer, and author whose career with the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) spanned almost three decades, from 1945 to 1970. Parker played a crucial role in developing and establishing agricultural and medical libraries throughout the world.
  Parker was born in Traders Point, Indiana on January 23, 1910. She earned her B.S. in botany from Butler University in 1932, and her M.A. and Ph.D. from the University of Cincinnati in 1934 and 1936.
  After completing her Ph.D., Parker took a position as the head of the Department of Biology at Brenau College, a women's college in Gainesville, Georgia. She returned briefly to the University of Cincinnati in 1938 to teach Plant Ecology, before becoming the head of the Biology Department at St. Mary's College in Notre Dame, Indiana in 1939. In 1944, Parker again took on a new role, this time as assistant curator of the herbarium and assistant editor of The American Midland Naturalist journal at the University of Notre Dame.
  Parker joined the Rockefeller Foundation in 1945 as a temporary Bibliographic Assistant in the Mexican Agricultural Program (MAP). She was promoted to Bibliographer and Librarian of the MAP in 1947, and held this position in Mexico until 1958. A 1960 RF Newsletter profile of Parker enumerated her invaluable contributions to the MAP's agricultural library: "During the years she was in Mexico she amassed and organized the library's collection of texts and references, atlases and maps, bulletins, theses, microfilms, and periodicals; conducted seminars on the use of the library; published a manual on the subject; and maintained a reference service which dealt with a far wider range of questions than one would expect in a library serving research in the development of basic food crops for Mexico." She also edited scholarly papers and reports, translated scientific papers, and reported on Mexican agricultural conferences for RF staff. Former MAP director J. George Harrar offered a concise summary of Parker's work: "the program could not run without her," he said.
  Parker's reputation as a highly skilled librarian and bibliographer ensured that her expertise and guidance were in high demand. Between 1956 and 1959, Parker traveled extensively for the Foundation, advising on the establishment or development of agricultural and medical libraries in Mexico, Honduras, Columbia, India, Thailand, and the Philippines, among others. From 1958-1959, Parker was stationed in India, working as a library advisor to the Foundation's Indian Agricultural Program.